<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>blog on Judica, Inc</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/</link><description>Recent content in blog on Judica, Inc</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&amp;copy; Judica, Inc 2022 | contact@judica.org | &lt;a class='darkmode-switch'> dark/light theme&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://judica.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>RoadMap or Load o' Crap?</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-27/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-27/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 27 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
I know, I know.
God forbid, a roadmap. People hate roadmaps. As I&amp;rsquo;ve noted before:
Bitcoin Eschews Roadmaps and Agendas. I provide this maxim to make clear that this document is by no means an official roadmap, narrative, or prioritization.</description></item><item><title>The History and Future of Sapio</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-26/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-26/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 26 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Sapio began as little more than a slide in presentations I would give on what BIP-119 could be with the support of a programming environment.
While my conceptions of what could be built with CTV were about on-par with where they are today, the tools available were very clunky.</description></item><item><title>Decentralized Autonomous Organizations (DAOs) Will Save Bitcoin</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-25/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-25/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 25 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
The title of this article is a joke. Gotcha!
Decentralized Autonomous Organization is pretty much what&amp;rsquo;s called an orphan initialism. So while DAO doesn&amp;rsquo;t really mean anything is decentralized, autonomous, or an organization, but the term DAO has stuck around anyways.</description></item><item><title>POWSWAP: Oracle Free Bitcoin Hashrate Derivatives</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-24/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-24/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 24 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Today&amp;rsquo;s post is near and dear to my heart &amp;ndash; years ago I put up an interest form for powswap.com, but as I went down the rabbit hole I realized how badly I wanted generic tooling to automate the building of these which is partly what led to Sapio!</description></item><item><title>Derivatives and Options For Bitcoin</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-23/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-23/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 23 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
In today&amp;rsquo;s post we&amp;rsquo;re going to talk about derivatives and options. Hoooo Boy!
Let&amp;rsquo;s define an Option: An option is a contract that gives the holder the right to take an action to the detriment of a counterparty.</description></item><item><title>NFTs Part Two: Auctions, Royalties, Mints, Generative, Game Items</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-22/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-22/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 22 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
I promised you a few things a few days ago:
We&amp;rsquo;d see how to do royalties in a sale We&amp;rsquo;d see how to do a Dutch auction We&amp;rsquo;d see how to do batch mints We&amp;rsquo;d see how to make generative art and one thing I didn&amp;rsquo;t</description></item><item><title>Packaging Sapio Applications</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-21/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 21 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Today&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a cheat day for me &amp;ndash; not really &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; content, but mostly stuff re-packaged1 from learn.sapio-lang.org.
But it belongs in the series, and is it really plagarism if I wrote it myself?</description></item><item><title>Oracles, Bonds, and Attestation Chains</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-20/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-20/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 20 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Today&amp;rsquo;s post is going to be a bit lighter weight than yesterday&amp;rsquo;s. We&amp;rsquo;ll cover some high level concepts around oracles and then look at some Sapio.
The genesis of this line of inquiry was a conversation with Robin Linus that led to a pretty cool whitepaper, so definitely read that if you find this post compelling.</description></item><item><title>Part One: Implementing NFTs in Sapio</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-19/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-19/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 19 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
For today&amp;rsquo;s post we&amp;rsquo;re going to build out some Sapio NFT protocols that are client-side verifiable. Today we&amp;rsquo;ll focus on code, tomorrow we&amp;rsquo;ll do more discussion and showing how they work. I was sick last night (minor burrito oriented food poisoning suspected) and so I got behind, hence this post being up late.</description></item><item><title>Sapio Studio Payment Pool Walkthrough</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-18/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-18/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 18 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Today&amp;rsquo;s post will be a pretty different format that usual, it&amp;rsquo;s basically going to be a pictorial walk through of the Sapio Studio, the frontend tool for Sapio projects. As an example, we&amp;rsquo;ll go through a Payment Pool contract to familiarize ourselves.</description></item><item><title>A Defense of Having Fun (and maybe staying poor)</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-17/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-17/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 17 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
A short story. I want to tell first. I recently made friends with Eugene, this really smart 19 year old Cal dropout, when I was visiting Miami for the NFT bachanal around Art Basel.</description></item><item><title>Composability in Sapio Contracts</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-16/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-16/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 16 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Who here has some ERC-20s or 721s1? Anyone? No one? Whatever.
The Punchline is that a lotta fuss goes into Ethereum smart contracts being Turing Complete but guess what? Neither ERC-20 nor 721 really have anything to do with being Turing Complete.</description></item><item><title>Decentralized Coordination Free Mining Pools</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-15/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-15/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 15 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Long time no see. You come around these parts often? Let&amp;rsquo;s talk mining pools.
First, let&amp;rsquo;s define some things. What is a pool? A pool is a way to take a strongly discontinuous income stream and turn it into a smoother income stream.</description></item><item><title>Payment Channels in a CTV+Sapio World</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-14/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-14/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 14 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Lightning Lightning Lightning Everybody loves Lightning. I love Lightining, you love Lightning. We love everyone who works on Lightning. Heck, even Chainalysis loves Lightning these days :(&amp;hellip;
We all love Lightning. But what if I told you we could love Lightning even more?</description></item><item><title>Payment Pools / Coin Pools</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-13/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-13/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 13 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Payment Pools are a general concept for a technique to share a single UTXO among a group. They&amp;rsquo;ve been discussed for a couple years1, but now that Taproot is active are definitely more relevant! In this post we&amp;rsquo;ll go through some really simple Payment Pool designs before turning it up a little bit :)</description></item><item><title>Congestion Control</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-12/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-12/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 12 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Congestion is an ugly word, eh? When I hear it my fake synthesia triggers green slime feeling, being stuck in traffic with broken AC, and ~the bread line~ waiting for your order at a crowded restaurant when you&amp;rsquo;re super starving.</description></item><item><title>Inheritence Schemes for Bitcoin</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-11/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-11/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 11 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
You are going to die. Merry Christmas! Hopefully not any time soon, but one of these days you will shuffle off this mortal coil.
When that day comes, how will you give your loved ones your hard earned bitcoin?</description></item><item><title>Building Vaults on Bitcoin</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-10/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-10/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 10 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
A &amp;ldquo;Vault&amp;rdquo; is a general concept for a way of protecting Bitcoin from theft through a cold-storage smart contract. While there is not formal definition of what is and is not a Vault, generally a Vault has more structure around a withdrawal than just a multisig.</description></item><item><title>Sapio Primer</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-9/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-9/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 9 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
We&amp;rsquo;re through the basics sections of the Advent calendar ow! Time for some more… specific content on the bleeding edge!
This post is your introduction to the world of Sapio. Sapio is the programming framework I&amp;rsquo;ve been developing for Bitcoin Smart Contracts.</description></item><item><title>Contracting Primitives and Upgrades to Bitcoin</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-8/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-8/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 8 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
In this post we&amp;rsquo;ll rapid fire roll through a bunch of different smart contract primitives, existing and proposed. For a more thorough reading, links will be provided.
BIP-119 CTV CheckTemplateVerify CTV is a general purpose smart contract opcode with full enumeration, no dynamic state, no recursion, and primarily works through validation.</description></item><item><title>Review of Smart Contract Concepts for Bitcoin</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-7/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-7/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 7 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
In this post we&amp;rsquo;ll review a concepts for thinking about different types of smart contract capabilities and the implications of their availability.
Recursive v.s. Non Recursive Recursive is pretty much just a fancy way of saying &amp;ldquo;loops&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>What's Smart about Smart Contracts: Bitcoin Maxi Edition</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-6/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-6/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 6 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Now that we&amp;rsquo;ve established the four pillars of Privacy, Decentralization, Self Custody, and Scalability, let&amp;rsquo;s get into smart contracts. But first…
DOES BITCOIN HAVE SMART CONTRACTS? There is a lot of fuss around if bitcoin has or doesn&amp;rsquo;t have smart contracts, and this is usually people talking past one another.</description></item><item><title>Pillars of Bitcoin: Privacy</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-5/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-5/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 5 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Privacy is foundational to Bitcoin. Fundamentally, we care about censorship resistance so folks can&amp;rsquo;t stop you from doing activity they can tell you&amp;rsquo;re doing… but what if they couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell you were doing anything at all?</description></item><item><title>Pillars of Bitcoin: Decentralization</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-4/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-4/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 4 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Many may have tried, but few have successfully characterized what &amp;ldquo;being decentralized&amp;rdquo; means in an objective / quantitative sense. Instead, we&amp;rsquo;re left with soft &amp;ldquo;know it when I see it&amp;quot;s.
Decentralization may be a pillar of Bitcoin with a lotta fanfare, but it&amp;rsquo;s still just a means to an end.</description></item><item><title>Pillars of Bitcoin: Self Custody</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-3/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-3/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 3 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
Not your keys, not your coin. A simple maxim often repeated by Bitcoiners, but an important one. Why?
That thing about the gold standard you probably heard before: In the existing financial system, your assets aren&amp;rsquo;t really your assets.</description></item><item><title>Pillars of Bitcoin: Scalability</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-2/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
Welcome to day 2 of my Bitcoin Advent Calendar. You can see an index of all the posts here or subscribe at judica.org/join to get new posts in your inbox
This is the first of four posts in an advent mini-series about four fundamental pillars of Bitcoin. I know, I know, a series within a series. What am I, nuts? But it&amp;rsquo;s important that we begin our journey by setting the stage with a few big picture objectives for Bitcoin before we get into why Smart Contracts matter.</description></item><item><title>Day 1: Rubin's Bitcoin Advent Calendar</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/advent-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/advent-1/</guid><description>This post is syndicated from rubin.io.
What says Christmas more than an Advent Calendar to count the days till Santa comes? Honestly, I&amp;rsquo;m not too sure, I&amp;rsquo;m a Jew. Happy Hanukkah everyone! But in the spirit of the season, I figured the community would love a series of blog posts (one a day) discussing the future of Bitcoin and Smart Contracts.
You can find an index of all the posts here.</description></item><item><title>From the Sapio Zoo: HODL Chicken + Tux Preview</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/hodl-chicken/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/hodl-chicken/</guid><description>An on chain game of chance.</description></item><item><title>Sapio Tutorial Sneak Peak</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/sapio-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/sapio-tutorial/</guid><description>&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;ve been hard at work getting Sapio ready for release, but I figured it would be a good time to
share some early documentation &amp;amp; basic tutorial to make &lt;a href="https://judica.org/sapio/">Sapio&lt;/a> a little more concrete.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enjoy the sneak peak!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title> The Urgency of Rearchitecting Bitcoin's Mempool</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/mempool/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/mempool/</guid><description>A deep dive into understanding some of the architectural challenges in Bitcoin&amp;rsquo;s mempool
and where future research may make improvements.</description></item><item><title>$50,000 Grant from 100x Group (BitMEX)</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/100x-grant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/100x-grant/</guid><description>Judica to use the funds to improve the mempool.</description></item><item><title>Sapio @ Reckless VR Meetup</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/sapio/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/sapio/</guid><description>A talk on Sapio at Reckless VR which explains how Sapio works by exploring an
implementation, bug fixes, and improvements to Blockstream&amp;rsquo;s Liquid deposit contracts.</description></item><item><title>$1,000 Grant from Delphi Digital</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/delphi-grant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/delphi-grant/</guid><description>Leading crypto analytics firm makes strong commitment to funding open source development</description></item><item><title>$10,000 Grant from ACINQ SAS</title><link>https://judica.org/blog/acinq-grant/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://judica.org/blog/acinq-grant/</guid><description>ACINQ answers the call to organize an effort around improving the mempool.</description></item></channel></rss>